A Guide to the Papers of F. Scott Fitzgerald, [1915]-1971, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of F. Scott Fitzgerald, [1915]-1971, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6177, etc.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
6177: Deposit, November 30, 1959 6177-a: Purchase, February 19, 1963 6177-b: Purchase, July 16, 1963 6177-c: Deposit, December 19, 1963 6177-d: Purchase, January 8, 1965 6177-e: Purchase, January 14, 1966 6177-f: Deposit, June 27, 1967 6177-g: Archival transfer, October 15, 1968. 6177-h: Purchase, September 1, 1977 6177-i: Purchase, March 5, 2005
Biographical/Historical Information
See Matthew J. Bruccoli's A Brief Life of Fitzgerald.
Scope and Content
The Papers F. Scott Fitzgerald consist of literary manuscripts, correspondence and miscellaneous documents. The collection includes five original manuscripts, by F. Scott Fitzgerald and Zelda Fitzgerald: The Fiend, Her Last Case, Magnetism, Pat Hobby in Hollywood, and Show Mr. and Mrs. F to Number... which was written almost by Zelda Fitzgerald, with some editorial changes by Scott.
Along with original manuscripts, papers contain numerous letters that reveal the passionate and turbulent life of F. Scott Fitzgerald throughout his life and career. Much of the correspondence is with Ruth Sturtevant, his confidante throughout his Princeton years and during his courtship of Zelda Sayre. Deeply personal and very revealing, Fitzgerald conveys to Ruth his relationship with various women at Princeton, Minnesota, and Montana, including Ginevra King, his meeting of Zelda, his despair when Zelda broke the engagement with Fitzgerald, and the extreme joy when they, almost surprisingly, become married. His letters to Ruth also span his academic career at Princeton, revealing a difficult struggle to pass classes in order to be eligible for the Triangle Club. Included in his letters to Ruth are poems, sketches, and elaborate stories, where he often portrayed Ruth as the main character of the story.
Other correspondents include F. P Adams, David A. Balch, [James V.] Barret, Mary Brown, Ruth A. Conley, Alfred Dashiel, John Dos Passos, Zelda Fitzgerald, Joseph Hergesheimer, Dayton Kohler, Charles MacArthur, George Northrop, Isabel Owens, Horace F. Simon, and Alycia Wootton. Many of these letters discuss the articles and novels he was in the process of writing, in particular Tender is the Night.
The final series, Miscellaneous Documents, includes the "Author's Apology" signed by F. Scott Fitzgerald which he had tipped into the third printing of This Side of Paradise and the birth announcement of Scottie Fitzgerald in October of 1920. Also included is a news clipping reporting the scandal resulting from Fitzgerald's appearance dressed as a woman at a Minnesota fraternity dance.
Arrangement
The Papers of F. Scott Fitzgerald are arranged in three series: Series I: Literary Manuscripts, is arranged alphabetically by title; Series II: Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by author; and Series III: Miscellaneous Documents, is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Manuscripts
  - Exiles From Paradise, by Sara Mayfield, 1971, Uncorrected bound proof, 307 pp. (Box-folder 1:1)
    #6177-h
  - The Fiend, by F. Scott Fitzgerald, [ca. 1934-1935], TMs, 8 pp. on 8 l.; with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:2)
    #6177
  - Her Last Case, by F. Scott Fitzgerald, [ca.1934 May-August], TMs, 48 pp. on 48 l. with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:3)
    #6177-a
  - Magnetism, by F. Scott Fitzgerald, [1928 January 12], TMsS, 34 pp. on 34 l.; with autograph corrections and additions. (Box-folder 1:4)
    #6177-b
  - Pat Hobby in Hollywood by F. Scott Fizgerald, 1942, TMs, 143 pp. (Box-folder 1:5)
    #6177-i
  - Show Mr. and Mrs. F to Number... by F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald, [ca. 1934], TMs, 8 pp. on 8 l.; with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - F. Scott Fitz[gerald] to "Dear Howard" [Ruth Sturtevant], [1915] May, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Fitzgerald laments that Ruth left, but "Helen Walcott lightened our misery." Ruth showed "extreme partiality" to one of Fitzgerald's friends, Mr. Obrien-Moore, because she "preferred his conversation." Fitzgerald explains, contrary to Ruth's understanding, that he could make it to her dance because "there are from three to five days between every exam." Fitzgerald expresses how devoted he is to Ruth and thinks they "could have a wonderful quarrel...because we're both blondes and could find the other's weak points." Wishes he was a "Washington parlor Snake." If both lived in St. Paul they would have a "desperate affair- wouldn't it be interesting." Writes that they may never see each other again (sketches a person crying), and ascribes Ruth some thoughts, "Is he trying to slip over some second-class stone-age sentiment when he's only met me twice in his life the fresh thing," but denies this sentiment because he's too "suspicious of blondes." Fitzgerald sketches three different portraits in letter: the "Princeton type," the "Yale type," and the "Harvard type." Asks Ruth how it is at Yale. Signs with "Suspiciously Yours" and draws his "trade mark" sketch. #6177
  - F. Scott Fitz[gerald] to Ruth Sturtevant, [1915] July 15, ALS, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 1:8)
    In list format, Fitzgerald tells Ruth that he is in Montana, visiting a classmate, 5,000 ft. above sea-level, on a 32,000 acre ranch, happy, healthy, wearing a cowboy costume, flirting with the village belle, and thinking frequently of Ruth. Describes the four day house-party he went to hosted by Catherine Ordway, of which he was disappointed because "she doesn't touch her famous running mate Ginevra King whom I declare to be the fairest [facinator] I ever hope to fall for." Discusses how beautiful Montana is, although he wishes they didn't talk with an accent. Fitzgerald does, however, desire to be in Washington D. C. with Ruth to "flock around" her like all the other men in D.C. Tells Ruth that she is "the first blonde [he] ever met that had it. But you've certainly got it. Haven't you lady." #6177-c
  - F. Scott Fitz[gerald] to Ruth Howard [Sturtevant], [1915 October], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Ruth met another girl who knew Fitzgerald, and Fitzgerald writes of the three girls he knows at Farmington, Aleda Bigelow, who is an "awfully good-looking dark haired girl," Margaret Armstrong, and Helen [James]. Fitzgerald and "Elkins O." talked about Ruth one night. Asks why Ruth tore up letter, and that she should rewrite it from memory and send it. Fitzgerald then mimics Ruth's large handwriting: "See I've filled almost a page already and I haven't said a single blessed thing." Mentions how it is "swell to be a junior." The faculty committee on non-athletic organizations refuses to let Fitzgerald go on the "triangle" trips "because of a chemistry condition," but is "allowed to keep the secretaryship and be Pres. next year" which is all he particularly cares about. Fitzgerald planning a trip up to see her. Asks Ruth to drop him a line and "answer all questions." #6177-c
  - [F.] Scott [Fitzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1915?] November, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l.; with envelope. (Box-folder 1:10)
    In a "blue and despondent mood." Sketches two figures, one a "Yale man after game," and the other "Princeton ditto after ditto." Mentions that he saw Stu Walcott during the game but the second half started before he could get over to him. The game was a "heart-breaker" and he "gloomed all evening." Spent the evening at the Elton Hotel with Geneva King, "another Westover girl," and another Princetonian. The Yale crowd kept taunting them. Wants to see Ruth "a lot right now" because she is "an awfully cheering person to talk to." Ruth would leave him in a good humor as opposed to "GK" [Geneva King] who leaves him in a "pronounced case of melancholia." Fitzgerald jokes about Ruth getting out the penitentiary. Nothing to look forward to except weeks of "grind and [triangle] work." Wonders why Ruth begins her letters to him with "My Dear Scott" which is too formal. Clears up misunderstanding about Fitzgerald comparing Ruth to Aleda: "Your resemblance to Aleda is purely in one thing which I won't put on paper as you'd surly show it to her and I don't think either of you would like it." Wonders if Ruth got "rushed to death" at the St. Anthony dance and probably met a wonderful Yale man. He would "illustrate" the letter but lacks the pep. Asks Ruth not to mention the football game. Signs "With Love" and a sketch of his trademark. #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Mrs. Sturtevant, 1916 January 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Fitzgerald apologizes to Mrs. Sturtevant, Ruth's mother, for not responding to her invitation, as he was sick with malaria and left for St. Paul immediately from the infirmary, and thus was not able to get her invitation. #6177
  - [F.] Scott [Fitzgerald] to [Ruth Sturtevant], [1916 February 9], ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l.; with envelope. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Jokingly admonishes Ruth for her "cold, formal letter," and sketches a picture of him at the North Pole with caption: "I want to get warm-I've just been reading one of Ruth Sturtevant's notes." Then wonders why she always mentions in her letters that they have only known each other a little while. He writes that Time is the only remedy and, to all intents and purposes, he has known her all his life. Here Fitzgerald sketches two baby carriages, one with "Scott" and the other with "Ruth" and they both say "GOO!" to each other. Wonders how her time at the Yale Prom went. The Doctor ordered Fitzgerald to stay at St. Paul through the winter. Besides Fitzgerald, Elizabeth Clarkson is the only one left "of the four" who were originally sick. Elizabeth and Fitzgerald spent the afternoon "playing calls on grim, unsympathetic matrons who looked quizzicly [sic] at us." Claims he is much more "a prompt correspondent" than Ruth, but that Ruth is the "one girl between [Fitzgerald] and social starvation." Encloses a picture of Bob Dunn, "One of the invalids and the prize parlor-Snake of St. Paul," but adds in pencil: "Can't find darned old picture- will put it in my next." Discusses how Sandra's ex-fiancé ran off with another woman (draws two stick figures running to train station). Fitzgerald explains how he is surrounded by holy pictures, but "turned them all to the wall." Signs "Love Scott" and sketches his "trade mark." #6177-c
  - [F.] Scott [Fitzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1916] March and April 9, ALS, 12 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Decides Ruth is "awfully nice" and states he is going to see more of her. Tells her it is going to be a long letter, and separates March section of letter into 13 parts: 1. Ruth must send picture of her to Fitzgerald so he could wake up to her every morning (sketches Fitzgerald in pajamas kneeling to Ruth's picture with caption: "True Devotion" or "The Idol Worshipper." 2. He just got a Chalmers. 3. "Alida Shoebutton Bigelow" told Fitzgerald that Ruth performed well on the piano in her recital. Asks her, "Are you really fat?" and sketches a heavy set woman lifting barbells. 4. Writes a story: "'Little Minnie McCloskey' or 'Girlhood hopes and dreams' or 'Life at Farmington' (A story for Young Females)," about a secret gathering of girls, including Ruth. They decide to do a prank, which is to hang Miss Porter. 5. Fitzgerald just read Sub-Deb and asks Ruth to please read Booth Tarkington's new book, Seventeen. 6. Compares Ruth to Ginevra. 7. Explains that picture of him was taken when he was sixteen. 8. Asks Ruth to read Town Topics for January 27th [1916?]. 9. Received an offer to be a female impersonator in a vaudeville act. 10. A man wanted to meet Fitzgerald when he saw a picture of him dressed as a woman, and Fitzgerald asks that he be poisoned. 11. When Ruth is married will show her his scrapbook. 12. Fitzgerald claims he is conceited. 13. Ends with a quotation: "Beauty may be only skin deep, but curves is curves." Continues letter on April 9th. Writes that he is old and grey haired and sketches his face. Discusses the "Sweat girls." Fitzgerald writes of Mary Glassford "who I understand has been repudiated by Minneapolis 'Society' (they think they have one) for Painting, puffing and petting." Bob Dunn bet Fitzgerald a dollar that he wouldn't introduce himself to the Sweat Girls but they had already left. Fitzgerald misses Ruth and is mad that he couldn't see her. He tried at the Yale Game but the half started before he could find her (sketches picture of football game and stadium with caption: "Stop the game. I haven't seen Ruth"). Sketches a scene of a couple in St. Paul: "Oh! that you were a manicure lady and I your loving shoe clerk- How simple everything would be." #6177-c
  - [F.] Scott [Fitzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1916 April 12], ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:14)
    Writes a short story for Ruth called The Other Mission about Miss Blinkton [i.e. Ruth] meeting a "monkey-wrench, huge and ugly." Fitzgerald writes an Editor's note: "The omitted words in the wire tappers remarks are-(censored by the Distric of Columbia board of censors)." Fitzgerald then sketches a scene from the story. Then he claims that Ruth's last letter "had nothing in it" and thus he is writing a "letter with nothing in it." Fitzgerald then writes a poem to Ruth: "Ruth Forsooth In my youth In a fortune telling booth A lady with one lone tooth Said I would always be ruthe [sic] To tell anything which resembled the truth She was wrong was she not Or do you think I've got The mania for making a plot Of silly rot As she told the tot." He then begins to write a limerick but crosses it out and writes: "I think we'd better stop." He apologizes for being rude and asks her to write a letter that will "cheer up a poor defenceless [sic] invalid." Talks of an account of his "wierd [sic]"adventure but because some of it was "improper" it couldn't be published in the newspaper. Wonders if Ruth is getting over her January and February gloom but that the Yale prom will help out. Fitzgerald complains how dull life is in Minnesota but "we've managed to unearth two Minneapolis charmers." Fitzgerald glues clipping to illustrate The Other Mission. Signs "Love Scott" and sketches his "trade mark." #6177-c
  - F. Scott Fitz[gerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1916 August 16], ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:15)
    Fitzgerald worried that they are not writing as often and as much as they used to, and stresses that they "have got to have a big affair sometime, someplace." Claims that summer is not the time for writing letters because "summer is a time for action and not words." St. Paul is more lively as there have been "loads of visiting girls." Just returned from a trip to Lake Forest, Illinois. Two of the "big four," Courtney Letts and Edith Cummings, were out west on a ranch but Margaret Cary and Ginevra King were there. Also met Marion Clough and Helen James. Writes "This is absolutely the last summer where I'm going to take life easily and float around with girls. Next summer I'm going to get a job in a newspaper office and see what I can do in the way of supporting a wife and family (not that I have anyone in mind.)" Tells Ruth that he hasn't written to another girl since last May. Asks Ruth to write soon. Sketches his "trade mark" and writes a postscript that he is sorry to hear about Ruth's mother being ill. #6177-c
  - F. Scott Fitz[gerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1916 ? October 29], ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:16)
    Glad to hear Ruth is still in the "land of the living." Argues with postman that he has a letter from Ruth to give to him, but the postman always denies it. Expecting results from chemistry exam to see whether he is eligible for the "triangle" show. He thinks he flunked it. Talks about his summer where he met Marion or Martha Clough. Explains why Virginia Sweat didn't like him. Decides to include a picture of him, "a very athletic looking picture," (glued to letter) so she remembers what he looks like. Asks Ruth to send a similar picture. People are kidding him about being a priest. Fitzgerald wonders why, because he would "make the conversion of wild young females" his specialty. Still writing "triangle" lyrics. Returns to his need of a photograph from Ruth, and sketches her nose, eyes, and lips. He concludes with a limerick: There was a young lady named Ruth Who lived in a telephone booth Every day without fail She'd be calling up Yale And telling all things but the truth. [On margin is a small blood stain with caption: "gore from a cut finger. Pretty cold effect. Don't faint!] #6177-c
  - F. Scott F[itzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1917] January 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:17)
    Admits that he always writes Ruth in the "gloomiest sort of moods on the gloomiest sort of days." Tells her that her last letter was the best she ever wrote. Fitzgerald provides "Futuristic impressions" of the people they know: Sandra, Alida, Elkins, Stuart, Ruth, and Scott. Thanks for the invitation to meet on Washington's birthday, but doesn't know if he has an exam that day or not. Ruth would probably be embarrassed when they met. Wonders if Ruth, when they meet, will think: "What- is this the poor [nut?] I've been corresponding with off and on for almost two years. -Good night! This ceases to be funny." Saw the movie Seventeen, which Fitzgerald complains "isn't half as good as the book." Asks Ruth for a picture. Inquires about Ruth's roommate. Writes "I'm becoming a distinguished author." Plans on seeing Robert Frost lecture. Quotes Swinburne and asks for picture of Ruth again. On front cover of envelope is a self-portrait [?] pencil sketch. #6177-c
  - F. Scott F[itzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], 1917 March 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:18)
    Concerned about Ruth's mother being ill, which explains the tone of Ruth's last letter. Admonishes Ruth for refusing to send him a photograph because "his dresser is not littered up with girls pictures" as she thinks. Her picture would accompany his sister, cousins, and aunts. Discusses his favorite poem by Swinburne, Roccoco [sic], where he compares himself to the spurned lover in the poem. Has a bet with "a very dark haired man" that if he loses he would have to dye his hair and eyebrows black. Will send Ruth a photograph if he loses bet (Fitzgerald then sketches a scene of photograph handed over to Ruth with caption: "Here Delia for Easter" and response, "I give notice mum!") Fitzgerald hopes to see her at Easter as he is planning on going to Norfolk. Remarks that he is "very religious these days." Finally complains how he keeps flunking Chemistry, which is the only course he ever flunked, but cannot be eligible for anything until he passes it. #6177-c
  - F. Scott F[itzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1917 April 9], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:19)
    Complains that Princeton has become a "melancholy place" as everyone is rushing off to war but that he is not permitted because he is under twenty-one. He could join as a private, but that "hasn't the least attraction" to him. Decided not to go to Wilmington to see John Biggs. Apologizes for criticizing her "nice rotund handwriting" and that he talked about himself more than he should have, which "probably bored" her to tears. Fitzgerald says he is not usually like that: "blame it on the heat, the war, or the shock of seeing you." Claims Ruth embarrasses him because she is "one of these calm, cool, deliberate and ethicly [sic] superior persons who drop an occasional crumb of conversation and expect the other to scratch for it..." Would go to Wilmington if the girl Durham were there. Finishes with "This is a weary life- I hope we all get shot soon." #6177-c
  - [F.] Scott Fitz[gerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], 1918 [December 4], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with envelope (Box-folder 1:20)
    Writes to Ruth that he enjoyed Sonia, and that she should read Youth's Encounter, Changing Winds, T he New Machiavelli, and Tono Bungay. Discusses his relationship with [Zelda]: "My affair still drifts- But my mind is finally made up that I will not, shall not, can not, should not, must not marry- Still she is remarkable- I'm trying desperately exire armis" #6177
  - "George Washington" [F. Scott Fitzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1919 January ?], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Declares to Ruth he is in love [with Zelda]. He is aide-de-camp to General Ryan. Happy that the two "like each other again." Fitzgerald will be out in April. Signs "Your obedient Servant George Washington." #6177
  - [F.] Scott [Fitzgerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1919] June 24, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:22)
    Fitzgerald, in a fit of despair, writes to Ruth, the "only person in the world that knows the other half... I've failed- it's a great tragedy to me and I feel I have very little left to live for..." Fitzgerald asks Ruth to tear up letter, and ends by saying, "Unless someday she will marry me, I will never marry." #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1920 February], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope and news clipping advertising This Side of Paradise (Box-folder 1:23)
    Admits that he has finally landed on his feet. Asks forgiveness and sends her a belated wedding present. Mentions that he wrote to Ruth "a wild letter where my world collapsed last June." Acknowledges that he is a "fairly well established author," with stories being published in The Saturday Evening Post, Smart Set, and Scribner's, and a novel coming out in April [This Side of Paradise]. Admits that he is "probably" going to get married in March, "the same girl, of course." Tells Ruth that he is "immeasurably older" and would "rather talk to [her] sometime." Ends by saying, "Life is so damn odd!" #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Ruth [Sturtevant], 1920 March 26, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:24)
    Tells Ruth that he is getting married April Fool's Day. Doesn't know where they will live. His book came out "today" and is "frightfully excited." Mentions that he sold the movie rights to his story, Head and Shoulders, for 2,500 dollars. Wants Ruth to meet Zelda because she is "very beautiful and very wise + very brave as you can imagine- but she's a perfect baby + a more irresponsible pair than we'll be will be hard to imagine." Gives his address for the next ten years as being in care of Scribner's. Hopes they can have lunch or dinner. Ends by asking Ruth to read his book. #6177
  - F. Scott Fitz[gerald] to Ruth [Sturtevant] [1920 April 7], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:25)
    A short note telling Ruth that he is a "married fella. Isn't it odd?" Asks Ruth to call them because Fitzgerald wants Ruth to meet Zelda. #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to Ruth [Sturtevant], [1920 May 14], ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:26)
    Fitzgerald dismayed because there is "no swimming in Lake Champlain," which was the "shock of [their] lives," because if "Zelda can't swim she's miserable." Finally they found the "slickest little cottage" which put them in "the most jovial mood imaginable." Hopes Ruth is feeling better. #6177
  - F. Scott Fitzgerald to [David A.] Balch, [1920] June 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope (Box-folder 1:27)
    Responds to Balch's request for biographical information, providing some "facts" about his life. Writes that he began writing when he was ten years old and that he wears "brown soft hats in winter, panamas in summer, loathe[s] dress suits and never wear[s] one and prefer[s] people with greenish-grey eyes." #6177-c